A Guide to the Administrative Files of the Virginia Dept. of Welfare, 1940-1975
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Administrative Files of the Virginia Dept. of Welfare, 1948-1977
The Library of Virginia
30941
7 cubic feet (7 Boxes)
Virginia Dept. of Welfare
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by the Virginia Dept. of Social Services, October 31, 1980.
Historical Information
On March 13, 1908, an act creating the Board of Charities and Corrections was passed by the General Assembly. The name of the board was changed to the Board of Public Welfare by the General Assembly on February 27, 1922, and the state government reorganization act of April 18, 1927, created the Department of Public Welfare. The General Assembly, on March 30, 1948, approved a reorganization of the state government that merged the Department of Public Welfare with the Department of Corrections to form the Department of Welfare and Institutions. This merger proved administratively unsatisfactory, so following several years of study, the General Assembly passed an act on March 9, 1974, separating the agencies to form the Department of Corrections and the Department of Welfare. On February 20, 1981, the General Assembly changed the name of the Department of Welfare to the Department of Social Services, effective July 1, 1982.
The purpose and mission of the Department of Social Services are to provide an effective public assistance and social services system to meet the basic needs of less fortunate citizens in their home communities, to assist them in becoming self-sufficient and self-supporting, and to protect all Virginians by promoting a safe living environment. The Department of Social Services administers state and federally funded assistance programs through supervision and support of regional and local welfare boards and locally operated social service agencies which administer a variety of programs, including emergency and temporary financial assistance, Medicaid, food stamps, foster care, adoption services, and child and adult protective services. In additions to financial services and assistance with local programs, the Department of Social Services also manages several service programs itself, including child support enforcement, licensing, community services, newcomer services, volunteerism and AmeriCorps.
Scope and Content
Administrative files, 1948-1977 (bulk 1960-1973), include correspondence, board excerpts, brochures, budgets, conference materials, planning documentation, project and program documentation, reports, and standards. Some topics include public assistance, college and university social work programs, adult and child services, volunteers, the Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project and the Virginia Uniform Welfare Reporting System.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in original order.
Contents List
- Administrative files, 1948-1977.
  - Public assistance provisions, 1950-1961. (Box 1)
  - Public assistance, 1957-1960. (Box 1)
  - Food Programs, 1971-1972. (Box 1)
  - National Service Reform Project, 1972. (Box 1)
  - Health, Education and Welfare - Public assistance, 1968-1969. (Box 1)
  - Public assistance, 1951-1953. (Box 1)
  - Appealed cases, 1967-1970. (Box 1)
  - Settlements, 1972. (Box 1)
  - Health, Education and Welfare, Dept. of, 1962-1972. (Box 1)
  - Public assistance, 1953-1954. (Box 1)
  - Health, Education and Welfare, Dept. of, 1969. (Box 1)
  - Health, Education and Welfare, Dept. of, 1964-1966. (Box 1)
  - Board of Welfare and Institutions, 1961-1962. (Box 1)
  - Health, Education and Welfare, Dept. of, 1969-1970. (Box 1)
  - Health, Education and Welfare, Dept. of, 1968-1972. (Box 1)
  - Health, Education and Welfare, Dept. of, 19670-1971. (Box 1)
  - Health, Education and Welfare, Dept. of, 1967-1968. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with localities, 1968-1969. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with localities, 1965-1967. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with localities, 1968. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with localities, 1969. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with localities, 1969-1972. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with localities - Richmond City, 1968-1970. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with localities - Sussex County, 1960-1962. (Box 1)
  - Madison College, 1969-1970. (Box 1)
  - Mary Washington College, 1964-1970. (Box 1)
  - Longwood College, 1959-1970. (Box 1)
  - Clinch Valley College, 1969-1970. (Box 1)
  - Virginia State University, 1955-1973. (Box 1)
  - State Planning and Community Affairs - Cost Study, 1972. (Box 1)
  - State Cars - General, 1973. (Box 1)
  - State Cars - Assignments, 1966-1973. (Box 1)
  - State Cars - Accidents, 1971-1973. (Box 1)
  - Virginia Government Employees Association, 1968-1976. (Box 2)
  - Staff Development, 1951-1972. (Box 2)
  - Interagency Planners, 1974. (Box 2)
  - Foster Parents, National Conference for, 1970. (Box 2)
  - Foster Parents, National Conference for, 1971. (Box 2)
  - Child Care Task Force, 1973. (Box 2)
  - Social Service Redesign, 1971-1973. (Box 2)
  - Federal Income Tax for Child Placing Agencies and Foster Homes, 1949-1950. (Box 2)
  - Meeting and phone call notes, 1949-1956. (Box 2)
  - Child Welfare Reviews, 1968-1969. (Box 2)
  - Mental Health and Mental Retardation Services Board (Fairfax and Falls Church), 1971-1972. (Box 2)
  - Adult Services, 1973-1975. (Box 2)
  - Child Welfare - Other states, 1968. (Box 2)
  - Legal Task Force, 1974. (Box 2)
  - Corrective Action Report, 1977. (Box 2)
  - Quality Control and Validations, 1970-1974. (Box 2)
  - Madison College, 1959-1970. (Box 2)
  - Virginia State College - Norfolk Division, 1960-1969. (Box 2)
  - Norfolk State College / Virginia State College - Norfolk Division, 1964-1970. (Box 2)
  - Social Service Delivery System, 1971. (Box 2)
  - Adult Service Conversion, 1973. (Box 2)
  - Refugees, 1973-1975. (Box 2)
  - Refugees - Cuban, 1974. (Box 2)
  - Public Service Cost Effectiveness, 1973. (Box 2)
  - Project FIND (Food Assistance), 1972-1973. (Box 2)
  - Mobile Welfare Office (Chesapeake), 1970-1972. (Box 2)
  - Mobile Welfare Office (Chesapeake), 1968-1969. (Box 2)
  - Evaluation Method of Payment for Essential Equipment, 1969-1972. (Box 2)
  - Adult Services (SSI), 1972-1973. (Box 2)
  - Adult Services (SSI), 1974-1976. (Box 2)
  - Volunteers, 1968-1973. (Box 2)
  - Volunteers, 1974-1976. (Box 2)
  - Volunteers - Correspondence concerning Volunteerism Survey, 1975. (Box 2)
  - State Plan, 1973. (Box 2)
  - Minimum Standards for Child Placing Agencies, 1969-1971. (Box 3)
  - Heads Start, 1967-1974. (Box 3)
  - Clerical Aides, 1967-1971. (Box 3)
  - Clerical Aides - Report, 1969 May. (Box 3)
  - Clerical Aides - Report, 1969 Nov. (Box 3)
  - Clerical Aides - Report, 1970 June. (Box 3)
  - Public Assistance, 1954-1956. (Box 3)
  - Board excerpts, 1955-1956. (Box 3)
  - Claims against estates, 1950-1955. (Box 3)
  - Settlement of estates, 1959-1960. (Box 3)
  - Settlement of estates, 1960-1961. (Box 3)
  - Settlement of estates, 1966-1970. (Box 3)
  - Health, Education and Welfare (HEW), 1969-1970. (Box 3)
  - Health, Education and Welfare (HEW), 1971-1972. (Box 3)
  - Health, Education and Welfare (HEW) - Region III, 1967-1969. (Box 3)
  - Public Assistance, 1953-1954. (Box 3)
  - Board excerpts, 1965. (Box 3)
  - Economic Opportunity Act, 1966-1969. (Box 3)
  - Man-In-The-House ruling, 1968-1969. (Box 3)
  - Public Assistance, 1960-1967. (Box 3)
  - Public Assistance - Income/Allowances, 1966-1967. (Box 3)
  - Public Assistance - Payments, 1952-1953. (Box 3)
  - Public Assistance - Payments, 1956-1957. (Box 3)
  - Appeal cases, 1968-1969. (Box 3)
  - Progress Report, 1969-1970. (Box 3)
  - Brochures, undated. (Box 3)
  - Baccalaureate Manpower Development Project - Report, 1969. (Box 3)
  - Baccalaureate Manpower Development Project - Report, 1970. (Box 3)
  - Family Assistance Plan, 1970. (Box 3)
  - Richmond City, 1963-1972. (Box 3)
  - Franklin County, 1968-1969. (Box 3)
  - Personnel - Recruiting, 1970-1975. (Box 3)
  - Personnel - Retirement, 19. (Box 3)
  - Personnel - Temporary and summer positions, 1960-1969. (Box 3)
  - Personnel - Temporary and summer positions, 1970-1975. (Box 3)
  - Personnel - Vacancies, 1971-1977. (Box 3)
  - Personnel - General, 1967-1978. (Box 4)
  - Personnel - Grievance procedures, 1971-1975. (Box 4)
  - Personnel - Orientation, 1968-1975. (Box 4)
  - Personnel - Qualification Standards, 1975. (Box 4)
  - Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1968-1970. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - General, 1970-1974. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - General, 1972-1975. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Black institutions, 1971. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Community Colleges, 1969-1975. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Averett College, 1969-1975. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Bridgewater College, 1973-1974. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Emory and Henry, 1959-1970. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Ferrum College, 1960-1970. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Frederick College, 1963-1974. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - George Mason University, 1969-1970. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Hampton Institute, 1959-1972. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Marion College, 1960. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Mary Baldwin College, 1959-1973. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - St. Paul's College, 1963-1972. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Stratford College, 1960-1970. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Sweet Briar College, 1959-1970. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Tidewater Community College, 1972-1972. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - University of Richmond, 1959-1970. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - University of Virginia, 1958-1971. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Univsersity of Virginia - Newsletters, 1965-1976. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Virginia Commonwealth University / Richmond Professional Institute, 1957-1959. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Virginia Commonwealth University / Richmond Professional Institute, 1960-1969. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Virginia Commonwealth University, 1970-1975. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1960-1972. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1973-1975. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Virginia Union, 1959-1972. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - Washington and Lee, 1954-1970. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities - William and Mary, 1953-1971. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Alabama, University of, 1968. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Atlanta University, 1966-1968. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Case Wesstern Reserve, 1975. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - East Tennessee State University, 1965-1966. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Florida State University, 1961-1968. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Georgia, University of, 1965-1968. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Louisville, University of, 1966-1968. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Maryland, University of, 1961-1969. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Metropolitan State College, 1974. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - North Carolina, University of, 1959-1968. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Tulane University, 1959-1972. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - West Virginia University, 1961-1972. (Box 4)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - University of Tennessee, 1961-1971. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Louisiana State University, 1965-1968. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Howard University, 1964-1968. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities (other states) - Catholic University, 1969-1973. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities - Randolph-Macon Women's College, 1959-1969. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities - Randolph-Macon Men's College, 1959-1970. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities - Northern Virginia Community College, 1969-1971. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities - Old Dominion University, 1960-1971. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities - Roanoke College, 1956-1970. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities - Hollins College, 1959-1970. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities - Hampden-Sydney College, 1959-1971. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities - Lynchburg College, 1959-1970. (Box 5)
  - Colleges and Universities - Bridgewater College, 1956-1975. (Box 5)
  - Baccalaureate Manpower Development Project, 1970. (Box 5)
  - Baccalaureate Manpower Development Project, 1969. (Box 5)
  - Southern Regional Education Board (Manpower Project), 1967-1969. (Box 5)
  - Southern Regional Education Board (Manpower Project), 1970. (Box 5)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1969-1970. (Box 5)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1970-1971. (Box 5)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1969-1970. (Box 5)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1968-1970. (Box 5)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1969-1970. (Box 5)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1970. (Box 5)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1967-1969. (Box 5)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1970. (Box 5)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1970. (Box 5)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1970. (Box 5)
  - National Commission for Social Work Careers, 1968-1969. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1968-1969. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1969-1970. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1969-1970. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1967-1970. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1967-1970. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1969-1970. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Social Welfare Manpower Project, 1969-1970. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Uniform Welfare Reporting System (VUWRS), 1974. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Uniform Welfare Reporting System (VUWRS) - Manual and training, 1970-1973. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Uniform Welfare Reporting System (VUWRS) - Social Service Delivery System (SSDS), 19. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Uniform Welfare Reporting System (VUWRS), undated. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Uniform Welfare Reporting System (VUWRS), undated. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Uniform Welfare Reporting System (VUWRS) - General, 1972. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Uniform Welfare Reporting System (VUWRS), 1970-1971. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Uniform Welfare Reporting System (VUWRS), 1972-1976. (Box 6)
  - Quality Control, 1972-1973. (Box 6)
  - Foster Care, 1972-1973. (Box 6)
  - Foster Care, 1961-1971. (Box 6)
  - Welfare Recipient Eligibility System (WRES), 1973-1976. (Box 6)
  - Welfare Recipient Eligibility System (WRES), 1974. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Uniform Welfare Reporting System (VUWRS), undated. (Box 6)
  - Virginia Uniform Welfare Reporting System (VUWRS), undated. (Box 6)
  - Governor's Office, 1972-1973. (Box 7)
  - Child Welfare Services, 1970-1975. (Box 7)
  - Human Affairs Information System, 1974. (Box 7)
  - Financial appropriations, 1973-1974. (Box 7)
  - Child placement, 1970. (Box 7)
  - Adult Protective Services, 1972. (Box 7)
  - Aid to Families with Dependent Children, 1972. (Box 7)
  - Social Service regulations/reform, 1972. (Box 7)
  - Social Service regulations/reform, 1965-1972. (Box 7)
  - Title XIX funds, 1968-1971. (Box 7)
  - Child care centers, 1969-1970. (Box 7)
  - Work Training Program, 1968-1969. (Box 7)
  - Work Incentive Programs, 1968-1972. (Box 7)
  - Adoption Act, 1948-1960. (Box 7)
  - Quality Control, 1956-1970. (Box 7)
  - Reimbursable hospital rates, 1953-1971. (Box 7)
  - Inter-staff Committee, 1962-1969. (Box 7)
  - Inter-staff Committee, 1959-1961. (Box 7)
  - Migrant labor, 1957-1963. (Box 7)
  - State Advisory Committee on Public Welfare, 1948-1953. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence and Board excerpts, 1958-1965. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence and Board excerpts, 1965-1972. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1970. (Box 7)
  - Virginia Farm Bureau Federation, 1959. (Box 7)
  - Shenandoah National Park, 1961-1963. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1971. (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on Public Welfare, 1953-1955. (Box 7)
  - Advisory Committee on Public Welfare, 1948-1954. (Box 7)
  - State Board, 1958-1972. (Box 7)